{"tossups": [{"question": "A defector from this country conducted the first full recording of Wagner\u2019s<em> Ring Cycle</em> and led the Chicago Symphony from 1969 to 1991. A composer from this nation mocked Shostakovich\u2019s<em> Leningrad</em> Symphony in the \u201cIntermezzo Interrotto\u201d of one work and collected folk songs with his countryman, Zolt\u00b4an Kod\u00b4aly [koh-dye]. For ten points, George Solti and the composer of a<em> Concerto for Orchestra</em>, B\u00b4ela Bart\u00b4ok, hail from what nation, the subject of 19<em> Rhapsodies</em> by Franz Liszt?", "answer": "<b> Hungary</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Michael Fay\u2019s treatment at the hands of this nation\u2019s government caused outrage in the mid-1990s. This nation abolished trial by jury in the 1970s, and it hosts the annual Shangri-La Dialogue for world security. The People\u2019s Action Party of this nation frequently sued opponents under the leadership of its recently deceased first President, Lee Kuan Yew. This smallest member of the Four Asian Tigers is notorious for its ban on chewing gum. For ten points, name this island-state on the tip of the Malay Peninsula.", "answer": "<b> Singapore</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The tank was first utilized at, for ten points, what deadly World War I battle, in which over 600,000 allied troops were killed in fighting for a French river?", "answer": "Battle of the<b> Somme</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "That memorial to this event also contains a chair with a glass base for each victim, all of which are arranged to represent their relative locations when they died. Charles Porter\u2019s photography of this event shows Baylee Almon being carried by firefighter Chris Fields. For ten points, name this 1995 terrorist attack on the Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building by Terry Nichols and Timothy McVeigh.", "answer": "<b> Oklahoma City Bombing</b> or<b> OKC Bombing</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Counteracting this phenomenon incurs shoeleather costs, and Robert Gordon\u2019s triangle model views demand-pull as one of its three causes. This phenomenon is plotted against unemployment in the Philips Curve. Gerald Ford pledged to \u201cwhip\u201d this phenomenon \u201cnow.\u201d Unlimited printing of money in Zimbabwe and the Weimar Republic led to \u201chyper\u201d episodes of this. The Consumer Price Index tracks, for ten points, what economic phenomenon, the rise in the cost of goods and services?", "answer": "<b> inflation</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {}, {"question": "Sayyid Qutb was arrested and executed for plotting to kill this man. This man\u2019s anti-aircraft battery on Green Island was destroyed during the War of Attrition. This man, who outlined his ambitions in <em>Philosophy of the Revolution</em>, rose to power after deposing Farouk I as head of the Free Officers Movement. The Aswan High Dam was built by, for ten points, what predecessor of Anwar Sadat as President of Egypt?", "answer": "Gamel Abdel<b> Nasser</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The last verse of the Italian national anthem refers to an eagle which \u201cdrank the blood of Italy and [this country\u2019s] blood.\u201d Louis XV backed his father in-law during a succession conflict in this country, which broke out after the death of King Augustus the Strong. This country was established by Mieszko I of the Piast Dynasty. Austria, Prussia and Russia partitioned this country three times. For ten points, name this country, once in a commonwealth with Lithuania, whose capital is Warsaw.", "answer": "<b> Poland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 2016, it was announced that this civilization understood the trapezoid method from elementary calculus. Much of this civilization\u2019s scientific accomplishments were taken to the west after a 331 B.C. defeat at Susa by Alexander the Great. For ten points, name this ancient Mesopotamian civilization that used a base 60 counting system.", "answer": "<b> Babylon</b>ia or<b> Babylonian</b> empire (prompt on Mesopotamia before mentioned)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This president ran on the slogan \u201cPublic office is a public trust.\u201d This man granted Native Americans citizenship if they accepted an allotment of tribal land provided by the Dawes Act, which he signed. He ordered the leader of a \u201cPetition in Boots\u201d to be arrested after the \u201cArmy of the Commonwealth in Christ\u201d trespassed on the White House lawn, and he sent federal troops to Illinois to guarantee mail delivery. Coxey\u2019s Army and the Pullman strike were put down by, for ten points, what U.S. president who served two non-consecutive terms?", "answer": "Grover<b> Cleveland</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "As a child, this ruler was attacked by Tsuda Sanzo in the Otsu incident. This ruler\u2019s forces attacked striking gold miners in the Lena massacre. A human stampede occurred during this ruler\u2019s coronation at the Khodynka fields. The forces of this ruler violently cracked down on a demonstration led by Father Gapon, leading to Bloody Sunday. This ruler\u2019s son Alexei\u2019s hemophilia was allegedly cured by the \u201cmad\u201dmonk Grigory Rasputin. For ten points, name this last Romanov tsar who was overthrown in the Russian Revolution.", "answer": "<b> Nicholas II</b> of Russia", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The majority of these events occurred in the Pale of Settlement.", "answer": "<b> pogrom</b> (prompt on massacres, etc., of Jews) <b></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Ancel Keys studied this condition at the University of Minnesota near the end of World War II. Claudius\u2019 sister Livilla died of this condition after being immured in her bedroom.</b> <b>This condition can lead to (+)</b> <b>kwashiorkor, which presents with a distended torso and</b> <b>whose name translates as \u201cthe sickness the baby gets when the (*)</b> new baby comes.\u201d Relieving this condition must be done carefully to avoid electrolyte disorders. For ten points, name this condition of extreme malnutrition that affects nearly one billion people worldwide.", "answer": "<b> starvation</b> (accept<b> protein deficiency</b>; accept descriptions of<b> not eating enough food</b>, including<b> malnutrition</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>The Blanketeers were the first organized group to perform this action for the purpose of political reform in England. One of these events was called by the TUC in 1926 and</b> <b>defused by George V. The \u201cWinter of (+)</b> <b>defused by George V. The \u201cWinter of (+)</b> <b>Discontent\u201d was named for James Callaghan\u2019s</b> <b>inability to control these events.</b> <b>William Benbow popularized this concept as a \u201cGrand</b> <b>William Benbow popularized this concept as a \u201cGrand</b> <b>National Holiday\u201d in 1832. Arthur Scargill led one of these events that was shut down by</b> <b>(*)</b> Margaret Thatcher, who planned for that event by stockpiling coal. For ten points, name these events, a refusal of workers to work.", "answer": "<b> strike</b>s (accept<b> general strike</b>)  Page 10", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This ruler signed the Treaty of Montpelier with Henri, the Duke of Rohan. This ruler collaborated with Charles de Luynes to assassinate (+) Concino Concini. This ruler came to power after his father was assassinated by Francois Ravaillac, and his</b> <b>mother, (*)</b> Marie de Medici served as regent during his childhood. This ruler\u2019s father was Henry IV, and his First Minister was Cardinal Richelieu. For ten points, name this king of France and father of the \u201cSun King.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Louis XIII</b> of France", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}